Finding Aid for Margaret L. Clay Papers, 1963-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Margaret L. Clay Papers 1963-2003, 1988-1996
Clay, Margaret L.
6.5 linear feet
2012129 Aa 2
Margaret Leone Clay was a psychologist and researcher who focused her career on raising awareness for public health disparities and treating substance abuse. The Margaret L. Clay Papers provide evidence of her involvement with several health organizations in Northern Michigan, primarily the Community/University Health Partnerships and the Northeast Community Partnership for Prevention. Meeting agendas, minutes, executive board reports, and financial records comprise much of the collection.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received Alma Sutphen (donor no. 10785 ) in May 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Margaret Leone Clay was a psychologist and researcher who focused her career on raising awareness for public health disparities and treating substance abuse. Clay was born October 23, 1923, in St. Joseph, Missouri and then raised in Chicago, Illinois. In 1956 she earned a Bachelor of Science degree from the University of Michigan. Two years later she completed a Master's Degree in psychology at the University of Michigan and by 1962 she obtained her Ph.D. in psychology.
Clay spent the next twenty years working at the University of Michigan's Mental Health Research Institute, where she served associate research psychologist and assistant director. During this time she also received an appointment as lecturer in psychology (1963-1971) and assistant professor of psychology in the department of psychiatry. Upon her retirement in 1982, the University conferred upon Clay the title of assistant professor emeritus of psychology in the department of psychiatry.
Following her retirement, Clay relocated to Hillman, Michigan with her partner Phyllis Brooks and was self-employed as a human services consultant. Clay became involved as a board member on a range of health agencies in northeastern Michigan, including the Thunder Bay Community Health Service (1983-2006), the Northeastern Michigan Community Mental Health Authority (1993-2011), the Northern Michigan Regional Academic Community Health System (NMRACHS), the Northern Michigan Regional Community Board, and the Michigan Division of the National Council on Alcoholism. Additionally, in 1991 she co-founded the Northeast Michigan Community Partnership for Prevention.
Dr. Margaret L. Clay died March 17, 2012, in Hillman, Michigan.
The Margaret L. Clay Papers are significant for their illustration of late twentieth-century public health concerns in rural Northern Michigan. The documents demonstrate collaborative efforts to eradicate health outcome disparities in Alpena and Montmorency Counties. Additionally, the Papers constitute a rich source of material related to alcohol and drug prevention at the regional, state, and federal levels.
The Margaret L. Clay Papers provide evidence of her involvement with several health organizations in Northern Michigan. The collection is arranged into two series, Public Health Initiatives and Substance Abuse Prevention.
Subjects:
Clay, Margaret L.; Michigan Coalition on Substance Abuse.; National Council on Alcoholism and Drug Dependence (U.S.); Northeast Michigan Community Partnership for Prevention.; Thunder Bay Community Health Services.; Public health--Michigan, Northeastern.; Substance abuse--Michigan--Prevention.; Substance abuse--Research--Michigan, Northeastern.
- Public Health Initiatives
  The Public Health Initiatives series is arranged into two subseries: Thunder Bay Community Health Services (TBCHS) and Community/University Health Partnerships (C/UHP). The TBCHS is a non-profit corporation that operated clinics in the village of Hillman and the village of Atlanta. These files spans the years 1984-1993, during which time Clay served as President of the Board of Directors. Items within this subseries are organized according to their function. Examples of records include Board of Director meeting minutes, compiled financial statements, and grant applications. Covering the years 1991 -- 1998, the records in the C/UHP subseries are arranged first by format then by year. Found in this subseries are board meeting minutes, reports and analyses, evaluations, and financial statements from a W.K. Kellogg Foundation grant that funded Michigan State University medical students to train in underserved rural communities, one of which was the Thunder Bay area. Board meeting minutes and program evaluation represent the most comprehensive subseries of the series.
  - Thunder Bay Community Health Services
    - Board Materials 1984-1993 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Internal Communication 1993 (Box 1)
    - Compiled Financial Statements 1984-1993 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Grant Documents 1985, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Patient Census Reports 1985-1992 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Clippings 1991, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Community/University Health Partnerships
    - Founding Documents 1992, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Northern Michigan Regional Community Board 1993 (Box 1)
    - Planning Materials 1993 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws 1994 (Box 1)
    - Program Evaluations 1992-1995, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Directories 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Director's Reports 1995, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Committee Meeting and Strategic Planning Board Minutes 1993, 1994, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Committee Meeting and Strategic Planning Board Minutes 1994, 1995, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1992-1996 (Box 2)
    - Printed Literature undated (Box 2)
    - Michigan Health Professions Policy Papers 1996 (Box 2)
    - Chronological Files 1991-1996, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Clippings 1990, 1994 (Box 2)
- Substance Abuse Prevention
  Four subseries comprise the Substance Abuse Prevention series: Northeast Michigan Community Partnership for Prevention (NMCPP), National Council on Alcoholism and Drug Dependency, Inc. of Michigan (NCADD/M), the Michigan Coalition on Substance Abuse (MCSA), and Topical Files.
  - Northeast Michigan Community Partnership for Prevention
    The NMCPP was an alliance spanning four counties of Northeast Michigan: Alcona, Alpena, Montmorency, and Presque Isle. The group's mission was to examine community values, attitudes, and behaviors surrounding alcohol, tobacco, and other drugs. The NMCPP subseries includes materials documenting its governance, administration, finances, research, and activities from 1990-1996.
    - Governance
      - History of the Partnership 1994 (Box 2)
      - Bylaws 1991, 1993 (Box 2)
      - Policies and Procedures Manual 1994, 1995 (Box 2)
      - Ad Hoc Transition Committee 1994 (Box 2)
    - Administration
      - Board of Delegates Minutes and Evaluations 1991-1994, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - Board of Delegates Minutes and Evaluations 1994-1996, 9 folders (Box 3)
      - Executive Committee Agendas, Minutes, and Reports 1994-1996 (Box 3)
      - Staffing Proposals 1993 (Box 3)
      - Performance Appraisals 1995, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Finances
      - Starter Fund Application Materials 1991-1995 (Box 3)
      - Application for Year 04 Funding 1994 (Box 3)
      - Abstract for CSAP Supplemental Communications Grant 1994 (Box 3)
      - Evaluation Contract Proposals 1994 (Box 3)
      - CFCS -- Catholic Charities 1994-1996 (Box 3)
      - Budgetary Items 1995, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Research
      - Addiction Research Institute Workplans 1991-1993 (Box 3)
      - Descriptive Data Survey Reports for Northeast Michigan and Montmorency County 1992, 1993 (Box 3)
      - Surveys and Qualitative Studies of Northeast Michigan 1992, 1993 (Box 4)
      - Alpena Resident Surveys 1996 (Box 4)
      - Northeast Michigan Youth Surveys 1996 (Box 4)
    - Activities
      - Action Plan for Improving Outcomes & Reducing Risks 1991 (Box 4)
      - Leadership Retreat 1992 (Box 4)
      - Newsletters 1994-1996 (Box 4)
      - Objectives and Implementation Strategies 1994-1996 (Box 4)
      - Center for Substance Abuse Prevention Eastern Regional Workshop 1994 (Box 4)
      - National Prevention Conference 1993 (Box 4)
    - Partners
      - Four County Substance Abuse Prevention Workgroup 1990, 1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Community Resources 1991-1993 (Box 4)
      - Community Partnership Member List 1992 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Association of Community Mental Health 1993, 1994, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous 1989-1994 (Box 4)
  - National Council on Alcoholism and Drug Dependency, Inc. of Michigan
    Clay served as a member of the Board of Directors for the NCADD/M, which began in 1973 with the mission to provide education, information, and advocacy for those affected by alcoholism. Arranged by year, this subseries contains items such as Board of Directors Nomination Forms (1991), Board of Directors Handbooks (1992 and 1993), and strategic financial plans (1996). The records cover the years 1987-2003, of which a sizeable portion is from 1991-1994.
    - 1987-1990, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - 1991-1995, 18 folders (Box 5)
    - 1996-2003, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Michigan Coalition on Substance Abuse 1979-1993 (scattered), 7 folders (Box 6)
    The MCSA was a consortium of substance abuse prevention networks that first organized at East Lansing on December 16, 1977 with its primary purpose being to promote access to quality substance abuse services. This subseries, filed according to year, holds conference programs (1979), work plans and procedures (1988), minutes of board and executive committee meetings (1992), and bylaws (1993). Scattered across the years are printed pamphlets and brochures describing the individual organizations that composed the Coalition.
  - Topical Files
    The Topical Files subseries holds proposals, resolutions, and a number of legal documents relating to the state of Michigan raising its legal drinking age. Among the legal documents are a legal brief and judicial opinion delivered by the United States District Court, Eastern Division that upheld the Michigan constitutional amendment raising the drinking age to 21. Photographs in this subseries are undated but many originate from Clay's tenure at the University of Michigan.
    - Michigan Board on Women and Chemical Dependency 1984-1987, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Community and Family Prevention Workgroups 1990-1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Macomb County School Surveys 1963, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Office of Substance Abuse, Michigan Department of Health and the Drinking Age 1973-1979 (Box 6)
    - Office of Substance Abuse, Michigan Department of Health and the Drinking Age 1973-1979, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Clippings 1985-1995 (Box 7)
    - Prevention Network 1988-1992 (Box 7)
    - Fetal Alcohol Syndrome 1992-1994 (Box 7)
    - Publicity Photographs, circa 1970s, 1980s (Box 7)